<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd before the King at White-Hall, Jan. 30, 1674/5 at the anniversary commemoration of the martyrdom of King Charles I / by George Stradling ...</title>
            <author>Stradling, George, 1621-1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61710</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5782</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17016</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13034500</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13034500</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96812</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61710)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96812)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 400:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd before the King at White-Hall, Jan. 30, 1674/5 at the anniversary commemoration of the martyrdom of King Charles I / by George Stradling ...</title>
                  <author>Stradling, George, 1621-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Mortlock ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Printed by His Majesties special command"</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 34.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  John XIX, 15 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96812:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96812:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd before the KING AT WHITE-HALL, Jan. 30. 1674/5. At the Anniverſary Commemoration of the MARTYRDOM of King Charles I.</p>
            <p>By <hi>George Stradling,</hi> D. D. Dean of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> and one of His Majeſties Chaplains in Ordinary.</p>
            <p>Printed by His Majeſties ſpecial Command.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Mortlock</hi> at the <hi>Phoenix</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>s Church-yard, and the White Hart in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall.</hi> 1675.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:96812:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96812:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>St. <hi>Joh.</hi> 19. 15. the latter part of the Verſe.</bibl>
                  <p>—Pilate ſaith unto them, Shall I Crucifie your King? The chief Prieſts anſwered, We have no King but Caeſar.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a great and common fault of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind to be over-curious in finding out the reaſons of Gods Providence, every one preſuming to ſound that bottomleſs <hi>Deep</hi> with his own ſcant line and plummet. Sin and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are ſo nearly related, that when the Lord has markt any one with ſome ſignal Judgement, we preſently raiſe hue and cry againſt him and are ready to fall upon him as one ſingled out for deſtruction, thinking that warrant enough to condemn <hi>whom God has ſmitten,</hi> and to make him the executioner of our raſh and unad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed ſentences. <hi>Who did ſin; this man, or his Parents, that he was born blind?</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 9. 2.</note> was once the queſtion of Chriſts Diſciples; and the beſt of us are apt enough to make too particular applications to perſons, to meaſure the hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſneſs of their offences by the greatneſs of their viſible ſufferings. Thus the Barbarians ſeeing a Viper faſtned to St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s hand, <note place="margin">Act. 28. 4.</note> immediately vote him no leſs than a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96812:3"/> murderer; the uncharitable errour too of ſome, in the caſe of thoſe Galileans <hi>whoſe blood Pilate had mingled with their Sacrifices.</hi> St. Luke 13. 1. <note place="margin">Luk. 13. 1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>If ſuch concluſions as theſe ſhould paſs for good, we ſhould inevitably <hi>condemn the generation of Gods Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> who commonly have a double portion of temporal afflictions; Every judgement on the holieſt perſon ſhould then be conſtrued a Reprobation; He that eſcapes the laſh here, ſhould then be the Son, and he that ſmarts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, the Baſtard; and by this argument we ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that God loves the Tents of Robbers more than <hi>the place where his honour dwelleth,</hi> as oft as he ſpares their Dens and fires his own Temple.</p>
               <p>I need not tell you how ſevere ſome of late have been in their reflections not only on private but publick perſons, even to the branding of Gods own Vicegerents and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly our late Soveraign, whoſe greateſt Crime 'twas to have been Unhappy. Their words as well as actions have ſufficiently expreſt their Charity to Him on this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, nothing having been more familiar with them than to make his ſufferings an argument of Gods rejecting Him, and a Plea for all thoſe affronts they ſhould offer to his Perſon or Dignity. The <hi>Mene Tekel</hi> was legible to every Paſſer by; Each one, though never ſo unlearned, could decipher the bloody characters, and pronounce the fatal ſentence; <hi>God hath forſaken him, perſecute and take him, for there is none to deliver him,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 71. 9.</note> was the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of our modern Sons of <hi>Belial</hi> againſt this our <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid;</hi> not conſidering that Princes have their failings as well as other men, That no condition whatſoever is exempt from a Divine Judgement, No Lawrel of proof againſt God's Thunderbolts, nor any Crown a ſufficient fence againſt an Almighty ſtroke; That God is pleaſed ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to exerciſe his Soveraign power and Empire over the Great ones of the Earth, to teach their Scepters to bow to his; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>v.</hi> Pſal. 106. 32.</note> That the Beſt of Kings may be the unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96812:3"/> here, and be puniſhed ſometimes not ſo much for their own as for their ſubjects faults; or, if for their own, only to brighten their graces, and to give them an advantage of purchaſing to themſelves more glorious Crowns in Heaven than they wear here on Earth.</p>
               <p>There is enough in this Chapter to ſecure this truth, where we may behold <hi>The King of Kings,</hi> in whom there was no <hi>Guile,</hi> no ſin but what of ours He took upon Him, <hi>ſuffering the contradiction of ſinners,</hi> made the very <hi>ſcorn of men and the outcaſt of the People:</hi> And after ſuch an example it can be no ſtrange thing to ſee his Deputy ſo ill treated, who as innocent as he was, was not impeccable, and yet ſo innocent and vertuous too, that all the Records of Hiſtory can ſcarce furniſh us with ſo excellent a Prince nor perhaps with ſo unfortunate, as if God had raiſed him up like another St. <hi>Paul</hi> to ſhew how great things he ſhould <hi>ſuffer</hi> as well as do for Him; <note place="margin">Act. 9. 16.</note> One whoſe Afflictions were great as Himſelf, and only leſs than his Saviours, but withal ſo like that 'tis hard to diſtinguiſh them; Each of them undergoing the Page<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antry of a Judicial tryal, delivered up out of envy to the rage and malice of an incenſed Rout and the Power of a corrupt Judge. And yet as corrupt as our Saviours was, he was ſtill a Judge, as Lawful a one as the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Power could make him; whereas Ours here had neither the Authority of a <hi>Pilate,</hi> nor yet the Innocence or Compaſſion. 'Twas <hi>Pilate</hi>'s ſad fate to conteſt with an enraged multitude, whom 'twas unſafe to diſpleaſe, and as dangerous to humour. On the one hand, violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to oppoſe them, was to reſiſt a torrent, to draw upon himſelf the hatred of a whole Nation, and perhaps <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi>'s too; and on the other, to gratifie them, was to make himſelf his own Enemy by caſting the Innocent; ſo that <hi>Pilate</hi> could neither well abſolve Chriſt, nor yet Condemn him. In this ſad ſtreight ſee how uneaſie he is under the apprehenſion of his own guilt and the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96812:4"/> Peoples fury, the former the much heavier load of the two, which he uſes all poſſible arts to ſhift off.</p>
               <p n="1">1. By endeavouring to clear our Saviours Innocence, the Judge himſelf becoming his Advocate and Jury too, paſſing his Verdict of not guilty, <hi>I find in Him no fault at all.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 18. 38.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. By expoſing Him all in blood as a ſpectacle of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery to excite their pitty and Compaſſion, <hi>Behold your King.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">c. 19. 14.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. By ſeeking to divert their rage on one who did really deſerve it, as being both a Traytor and a Murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; <note place="margin">c. 18. 40.</note> and when all this would not do,</p>
               <p n="4">4. He produceth his laſt and ſtrongeſt argument to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terr them from ſo horrid and impious an attempt, namely, That He whoſe blood they ſo much thirſted for, was not only an innocent Man, but a King; and, which was more, Their King; The offering violence to ſuch a perſon, being in his apprehenſion ſo unparallel'd a crime, that no precedent could warrant it; ſo that <hi>Pilate</hi> himſelf is ſtartled at the very thought of it, and in a juſt indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of being made the inſtrument of ſo foul a Treaſon breaks forth into this Pathetical queſtion in the Text, <hi>Shall I Crucifie your King?</hi> Which whether he did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally take him for, or only ſpake it by way of jeer and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſion, yet from the very ſuppoſition we may argue, How ſacred the Perſon of a King was held to be in the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Heathen and him none of the beſt, and of the worſt of Jews too by the anſwer they make him, owning his reaſon for good upon ſuppoſition, That Chriſt had been their King, <hi>We have no King but Caeſar:</hi> As if they ſhould have ſaid, True indeed, were this man a King, much more, Our King, we could have no tolerable Plea or Excuſe for thoſe our proceedings againſt him; But here is <hi>Error Perſonae,</hi> Thou miſtakeſt the Perſon, <hi>Caeſar,</hi> not this man, is Our King, and therefore take heed what thou doeſt, leſt thou make <hi>Caeſar</hi>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:96812:4"/> thine Enemy by ſetting up a Competitor againſt him.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">The Diviſion.</note> From the words thus explained we may clearly inferr this general Concluſion, That Every Natural and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Prince ought to be ſacred, ſupream, and conſequently Inviolable, and that
<list>
                     <item>1. By the Confeſſion of Heathens and of Jews; and that this was their Judgement, I ſhall endeavour in the firſt place to make out diſtinctly unto you.</item>
                     <item>2. And in the ſecond, I ſhall ſhew you, how vile theſe Jews were, how falſe to their God and to themſelves too, in owning <hi>Caeſar</hi> for their King, and diſowning Chriſt.</item>
                     <item>3. To compleat my diſcourſe, I ſhall give you the ſence of Chriſt, his Apoſtles and primitive Doctors as to matter of ſubjection to Soveraign Princes; and ſo cloſe up all with ſome application to our preſent Occaſion.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>I begin with the firſt thing in the propoſed order; namely, the judgement of Heathens as to the ſacredneſs of the perſons of Kings, imply'd in this Queſtion, <hi>Shall I Crucifie your King?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>The firſt Part.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">1. Of the judgement of Heathens.</note> A ſtrange thing this, to a <hi>Pilate,</hi> as indeed to all Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, with whom Monarchy was a ſacred thing, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a Divine, at leaſt, a Natural Original. That they deriv'd it from <hi>Jupiter</hi> is clear from their <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and thoſe high Titles they gave Kings of <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſo frequent among them. That 'twas founded in Nature, <hi>Seneca</hi> tells us: Nature, ſayes he, did firſt invent a King. His inſtance is in Bees, and he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves it alſo in other Creatures. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Natura com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta eſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem; quod &amp; ex aliis ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malibus licet cognoſcere &amp; ex apibus,</hi> lib. 1. de Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ, c. 19.</note> And indeed what was
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96812:5"/> the firſt man, in the deſign of his Creation, but an Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Monarch? <hi>Polyarchy</hi> came in with Sin and the Curſe, and Common-wealths are but Puny States to Monarchy. This is plainly confeſt by <hi>Tully</hi> who reckons it <hi>inter Notiora,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Omnes Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quae Gentes Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus quondam paruerunt.</hi> Cicero lib. 3. de legibus, initio.</note> among the moſt certain known truths, That all Nations of old were ſubject to Kings. <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Juſtin. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Juſtin</hi> ſayes the very ſame thing, and <hi>Tacitus</hi> particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly affirms this to have been the ancient Roman Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, in the very firſt words of his <hi>Annals.</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Tacit. Annal.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  </p>
                  <p>But beſides the unanimous conſent and inclination of all Nations to this form of Government, It's having been exerciſed by Fathers of Families in the firſt Ages of the World for at leaſt three thouſand years, ſtrongly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms it. That <hi>Noah</hi> had this power we may collect from <hi>Gen.</hi> 9. 25. <note place="margin">Gen. 9. 25.</note> And <hi>Abraham</hi> is therefore ſtiled <hi>A mighty Prince,</hi> c. 23. 6. <note place="margin">23. 6.</note> though his Principality exten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed not beyond the limits of his own Family, as being therein Abſolute and Uncontroulable. We do not read any where that <hi>Adam</hi> in his many hundred years Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy ever askt his Subjects Conſent; His Dominion was as abſolute over his Own as over the other Creatures, his Will a Law, and all his Dictates, Oracles. Such a ſucceſſive unlimited Monarchy as God did at firſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute; ſo was He pleaſed ſtill to continue in the Firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born. <hi>Cain</hi> had it upon this account and that by Gods own appointment, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. 7. <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 7.</note> From whence it ſucceeded in <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Family, Gen. 49. 3. <note place="margin">49. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>Reuben thou art my firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born—The Excellency of Dignity and the Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of Power</hi> (of Honour and Authority) that is. The Supremacy of both. This laſted all along in the Patriarchs line; He that begat, commanded; He that gave life might take it away; All power then remained in the Fathers hand, as all Law did in his breaſt. <hi>Jus vitae &amp; necis,</hi> derived from Nature, belonged to him by the right of nature; and to have reſiſted a Fathers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand then, had been a crime of the deepeſt dye. and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96812:5"/> when the Roman <hi>Manlius</hi> ſlew his Victorious Son with his own hand, he acted by the Authority of a Father as well as of a Magiſtrate. Which paternal power con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued among the Romans till <hi>Juſtinian</hi> took it away, ſo that before his time 'twas ſtill in force, though Chriſtianity forbad the uſe of it. A ſecond thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent to the former, was high honour and Reverence, which natural reaſon as well as God's Law taught men to pay unto Parents; <hi>Honour thy Father,</hi> being a Law written in the heart of man as well as engraven in ſtone, and which we therefore find given by Heathens to their natural Parents in as high a degree as ever it was by Jews or Chriſtians.</p>
                  <p>Now theſe two things, Supremacy and Honour, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted in natural Parents and owned as their due, were by the free and voluntary act of the People afterward transferred on the Political, when many Families be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came united into one Kingdom, and the very Title paſt along with the Power. Hence are Princes ſtiled <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres Patriae,</hi> and, as ſuch, retained the ſame Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and the ſame at leaſt if not a greater Reverence. For they were abſolute, their Empire knew no bounds in the early ages of the World, known by the name of <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, wherein, <hi>Arbitria Principum pro legibus erant;</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Juſtin. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> Their rule wholly Deſpotical, yet <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, juſt and legal, though abſolute and unaccountable. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ariſtot. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>pol. cap.</hi> 10.</note> Such a Government the Eaſtern People liv'd long un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and enjoy'd a great meaſure of happineſs by it; and therefore to ſpeak in <hi>Tacitus</hi> language, <hi>Addicte admodum regnabantur,</hi> they were moſt devoutly obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, no more queſtioning their Princes wiſdom than their Gods. Heathens knew no ſuch thing as a <hi>Prior pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo,</hi> their Reaſon could not conceive how any one could be ſup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eam and yet have another above him, nor find a Circle in Covernment leſs abſurd than one in Logick, as that which in their judgment would infallibly beget an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96812:6"/> progreſs. This was the Poets notion of a King, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Martial. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Epig.</hi> 17.</note> 
                     <hi>Qui Rex eſt, Regem, Maxime, non habeat.</hi> Otherwiſe he ſhould be a King and no King. And therefore 'tis very obſervable, that in all forms of Government there was ſtill Supremacy, a <hi>poteſtas Regia,</hi> abſolute and above Laws, even in the Roman Common-wealth after the expulſion of their Kings, inherent in the Perſon of the Supream Magiſtrate <hi>pro tempore,</hi> ſuch as were the Dictator and the Tribunes of the People, without which it had been impoſſible for them to preſerve peace and order among men. This rendred them <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſafe and unqueſtionable. 'Tis true indeed that there were different ſorts of Kings among Heathens according to the different Qualifications of Regal power in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Kingdoms. Some, though reſtrained by Laws, were yet truly Monarchs, not reſponſible, as ſupream, though not abſolute. Others had the Name and Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of Kings, being in effect but more ſpecious and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Subjects, as was <hi>Theſeus</hi> to the People, and the <hi>Spartan</hi> Kings to the <hi>Ephori. Cornelius Nepos</hi> ſtiles theſe latter, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cornel. Nepos in Ageſilao.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Nomine magis quam Imperio Reges,</hi> Titu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Kings, who, exceeding the bounds of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, were ſome of them ſentenced and Executed too by the <hi>Lacedemonians.</hi> But the Queſtion here is of Kings not reſtrained and fetter'd by conditional com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacts and agreements, but ſuch, as for the moſt part, were left free and unbound. To cite them to any Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal, was a thing no Heathen Subjects ever did, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed thought fit to do. <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> Joſeph. Jud. Antiq. lib. 15. c. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>Herodotus</hi> tells us, that <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byſes</hi> conſulting his Senate, whether he might lawfully Marry his Siſter, was anſwered, That they found no ſuch Law as gave a Brother power to take his Siſter to Wife: But that indeed they met with one which gave their Emperour free liberty to do what he pleaſed. When <hi>Herod</hi> was cited to appear before <hi>M. Anthony</hi> to anſwer for the murder of <hi>Ariſtobulus, Anthony</hi> ſaid
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:96812:6"/> openly, That 'twas not fit a King ſhould be queſtioned for what he did as King. I remember that <hi>Tully</hi> being to defend King <hi>Deiotarus</hi> before <hi>Caeſar,</hi> begins his Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the ſtrangeneſs and novelty of the thing, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him, that 'twas ſo unuſual a thing for a King to be accuſed, that before that time 'twas never heard of. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ita eſt inuſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Regem ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitis reum eſſe, ut ante hoc tempus non ſit auditum.</hi> Cic. Orat. pro Deiotaro.</note> So ſacred were the Perſons, ſo unqueſtionable the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Soveraign Princes over their ſubjects, that whereas 'twas held Parricide to affront natural Parents, to abuſe Theſe was in Heathens account no leſs than ſacriledge. No defects in Government could render them obnoxious to Juſtice, nor any crimes, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo enormous, dethrone them. They were <hi>Tuti Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perii Majeſtate,</hi> Their Majeſty was their Protection, and their Character, their ſanctuary; They were above the reach of thoſe Laws which Themſelves made; (Above the Cenſure and Penalties of them, not their Guidance and Direction;) and ſince they could diſpence with others for the breach of them, then much more ſurely with Themſelves who were the Authors of them. <hi>Nemo unquam Principi leges ſcripſit;</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Plin. Panegyr.</note> And, <hi>A Te exigetur Ratio, nos excuſabit Obſequium,</hi> ſayes <hi>Pliny.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tibi ſummum rerum judicium Dii cedêre, nobis obſequii gloria relicta eſt,</hi> M. Terent. apud Tacit. Annal. lib. 6.</note> No Law could puniſh nor any call Kings to account but the Gods, who as they gave them the higheſt Empire here, ſo did they leave their ſubjects nothing but the glory of obeying them. This was <hi>Pliny</hi>'s and <hi>Tacitus</hi> his Divinity, and much ſounder no doubt than what ſome Chriſtians have of late taught us, who will needs <hi>Principes in ordinem redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere</hi> as <hi>Buchanan</hi> phraſes it (like a Pedant, as he was) Reduce Princes to good order, by placing Tutors and Guardians over them to correct them for thoſe imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry faults which their own fancy moſtly creates and then heightens into Crimes.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>De jure Regni apud Scotos.</hi> Edit. Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgi 8. 1581. p. 6.</note> 
                  </p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:96812:7"/>
                  <p>By what has been ſaid it appears, That as Kingly Government was firſt founded in <hi>jure paterno;</hi> ſo that Kings themſelves were as abſolute and uncontroulable in their Dominions as Fathers were in their Families for ſome thouſands of years; A thing ever acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by Heathens, and never diſputed them but by Chriſtians. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Bell. Jagurth.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Impune quidvis facere, Id eſt Regem eſſe,</hi> was <hi>Saluſt</hi>'s definition of a Soveraign Prince, and all Heathens admitted it; who were ſo far from thinking it fit to puniſh him in his perſon, that 'twas Treaſonable with them to attempt it in Effigie. I need not tell you how much the Roman Laws provide for the ſecurity of their Emperours, and to this purpoſe I might cite ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them. But I forbear, and ſhall only add a little touching that reverence and honour Heathens gave their Kings; for the moſt part indeed too much, being ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious in this point even to exceſs. For I find it held unlawful, by the Eaſtern People eſpecially, for pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate men to gaze too much on their Prince, and unſafe to venture into his preſence unſent for. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſee <hi>Eſther</hi> durſt not appear before <hi>Ahaſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> till he held out his Golden Scepter to her. <note place="margin">Eſther 5. 2.</note> What eſteem Heathen ſubjects had for their King; we learn from <hi>Artabanus</hi> a <hi>Perſian</hi> ſpeaking thus for himſelf and the reſt of his Country men; <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Apud Xeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phont.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. We own it as the chiefeſt of thoſe many good Laws among us to honour and adore our Prince as the lively pourtraicture of the great Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver of all things. An Expreſſion not much differing from that of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 17.</note> 
                     <hi>Fear God, Honour the King.</hi> I might here preſent you with thoſe lofty Titles of Eternity and Divinity ſo frequently by the Romans be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon their Emperours and the like, more proper for Gods than Men; I might tell you how to abuſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96812:7"/> their very ſtatues was Sacriledge; How they ſware by the lives of their Princes (as <hi>Joſeph</hi> did by <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s, <hi>Gen.</hi> 42. 16.) <note place="margin">Gen. 42. 16.</note> 
                     <hi>per Genium Imperatoris,</hi> in <hi>Tertullian.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Apologet. c.</hi> 32.</note> Such Reverence did Heathens pay unto them as to ſo many Earthly Gods, from whom they ſaw they derived the ineſtimable benefits of Peace, plenty and Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; The main ground of all the Heatheniſh Idolatry.</p>
                  <p>No marvel then if <hi>Pilate</hi> (who being a Judge 'tis preſumed could not be ignorant of theſe things as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been bred and trained up under the Roman diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, and ſo well acquainted with its Laws and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes) comparing the affronts and indignities theſe Jews were now offering to one whom he ſuppoſed their King, with that high reſpect and honour he knew all other Nations, and eſpecially the Roman, expreſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards theirs, is here ſo much ſcandalized at the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of their Proceedings. 'Twas a new thing to him to ſee a King brought before him by his own ſubjects to receive his ſentence. <note place="margin">Joh. 18. 31.</note> 
                     <hi>Take ye him and judge him according to your Law,</hi> ſays he, not Ours; We have no ſuch Law whereby to judge, much leſs to put a Prince to death. This he charges them home with, and they to prevent the ſuſpicion of ſo ſoul a crime, deny Chriſt to be their King, but by owning <hi>Caeſar</hi> to be ſo, profeſs as much Loyalty and Obedience to him as <hi>Pilate</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf could pretend to, which brings in the ſecond point of the firſt part of the Text, namely the Judgement of the Jews as to the ſacredneſs of Kings perſons and their Exemption from Force or Judicial Tryal.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">2. Of the judgement of Jews.</note> 2. That Kings derived their Authority from God and not from the People; and therefore could be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſible to none but God for what they did, is a Truth clearly delivered by the Prophets; <hi>He removeth and ſetteth up Kings,</hi> ſays <hi>Daniel,</hi> c. 2. 21. <note place="margin">Dan. 2. 21.</note> 
                     <hi>He placeth them on their Thrones,</hi> ſays <hi>Job,</hi> c. 36. 7. <note place="margin">Job 36. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>By Him they reign</hi>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:96812:8"/> 
                     <hi>and by Him they decree Juſtice,</hi> Prov. 8. 15. <note place="margin">Prov. 8. 15. Pſal. 89. 20. 2 Chron. 9. 8. Prov. 21. 1. Pſal. 21. 3. 82. 6.</note> Their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adem, their Anointing their Scepter, their Throne, all are ſaid to be from God. As their <hi>Hearts are in his hand;</hi> ſo the ſame hand ſets their Crowns faſt upon their Heads. <hi>Dixi, Dii eſtis,</hi> is Gods language to Them, not the Peoples, For then the <hi>Dixi</hi> ſhould have been changed into a <hi>Diximus;</hi> nor ſhould the ſtyle be, By me Kings reign, but by Us, according to the modern Divinity. Conſider we a little how the firſt Jewiſh Kings were elected, and we ſhall find that the People had little or nothing to do in their choice. They in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>deſired a King</hi> but <hi>God gave him</hi> as He had long before deſigned him. <note place="margin">Act. 13. 21.</note> Nor do we find that the Jewiſh Kings ever ſtood much upon their Confirmation by the People, but as thoſe that knew their way to the Throne aſcended its ſteps without the Peoples aid. 'Tis true indeed, The <hi>People</hi> are ſaid to have <hi>made Saul a King in Gilgal;</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Sam. 11. 15.</note> But their making him there, was no more than their approving him. They did only add to the Pomp and Ceremony, not to the eſſence of the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution. For <hi>Saul</hi> was both nam'd and confirm'd King and had executed his Office before this ſolemnity, as appears from 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> chapters 10. &amp; 11. <note place="margin">1 Sam. cap. 10, 11.</note> The People could pretend no intereſt here, God having left them no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do but to admit and accept him. The ſame is as true of <hi>David</hi> too; <note place="margin">Pſa. 78. 71, 72.</note> God <hi>choſe</hi> him <hi>and took him away from the Sheep-folds, that he might feed Jacob his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Iſrael his Inheritance;</hi> Nay God himſelf owns the Inſtitution, Pſal. 89. 20. <note place="margin">89. 20.</note> 
                     <hi>I have exalted one choſen out of the People;</hi> The Exaltation was Gods, and the choice not Of but Out of the People. And as He did exalt; ſo did He anoint him with his own holy Oyle, an Emblem of his Soveraignty. A character not only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to Him, but to all his Succeſſors, <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Sam. 10. 27.</note> (Royal Birth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing equal to Royal Unction) to whom in token of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, the People paid homage and gave gifts, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96812:8"/> their Images on their Coynes, and began their <hi>Aera</hi> from their Reign; All marks of that ſoveraign Authority Kings had over them, and which was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver diſputed. For whatever the rebellious practices of ſome were (As there will be Rebels while there be Kings, and never greater ſtore of ſuch than among the Jews, whom the Prophets frequently ſtyle <hi>A Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious Nation)</hi> yet the opinion of the beſt and ſobereſt part of them was ever Orthodox as to matter of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to their Natural Princes, whatever they thought of Forraign ones, whom they lookt upon as Uſurpers.</p>
                  <p>This then being granted (as needs it muſt) That their Kings were ſupream, as holding their Scepters only from God; It will neceſſarily follow that they were account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to none but Him. And this is further demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrable from the <hi>Jus Regni</hi> mentioned 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. <note place="margin">1 Sam. 8.</note> where all the Acts of a Tyrannical King are at large deſcribed, but ſuch as the People could not chooſe but ſubmit to. 'Twas not a Law given for a Prince to Command, but for the People to obey by. It did by no means excuſe him from ſinning, but it did ſufficiently diſable them from puniſhing him. And therefore 'tis ſaid, when the ſolemnity of this Inauguration was over, <note place="margin">v. 10.</note> That <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel told all the words of the Lord unto the People that asked of him a King.</hi> He ſpake not to the King, but addreſt himſelf to the People and declared their Duty (For his duty was well known, it having been taught him by <hi>Moſes</hi> many Ages before, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.) <note place="margin">Deut. 17.</note> And the cloſe of all is this, ſince there is no help in man, they muſt only cry unto the Lord, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. 18. <note place="margin">1 Sam. 8. 18.</note> From whence it appears, that although what a King ſhould do were never ſo wicked, yet that he might do it with ſafety and impunity. Which is the expreſs do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Old Teſtament. Job. 34. 18. <note place="margin">Job 34. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>Is it fit to ſay to a King, Thou art wicked? Or to Princes, Ye are Ungodly?</hi> 'Twas not ſo it ſeems in <hi>Job</hi>'s dayes, nor
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96812:9"/> in <hi>Solomon</hi>'s neither; <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8. 2, 3.</note> 
                     <hi>I counſel thee to keep the Kings Commandment, and that in regard of the Oath of God; For he doth whatſoever pleaſeth him:</hi> and v. 4. <note place="margin">v. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>Where the word of a King is, there is Power, and who may ſay unto him, What doſt thou?</hi> No man without danger to his life and ſoul too, <note place="margin">Prov. 20. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>whoſo provoketh him to anger, ſinneth againſt his own ſoul.</hi> He pulls down the Kings, and Gods anger upon his head. Kings indeed have long hands, but the Almighty's are much longer and heavier, who will be ſure to puniſh the breach of that Oath the ſubject makes to his Prince, and thoſe affronts that are put upon his Vicegerent; He, who ſayes expreſly to <hi>Samuel,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Sam. 8. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>They have not rejected Thee but Me,</hi> will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret ſuch injuries as done unto himſelf. How dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous a thing it was for the Jews to diſobey an infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Authority, we learn from Deut. 17. 12. <note place="margin">Deut. 17. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>The man that will do preſumptuouſly and will not hearken to the Prieſt, that ſtandeth to miniſter there before the Lord thy God, or unto the Judge, even that man ſhall dye;</hi> where we ſee that to diſobey the ſentence given by the Judge and interpreted by the Prieſt, was preſent death by the Law of <hi>Moſes:</hi> much more, to reſiſt the commands of the Soveraign Prince, and that by the Teſtimony and conſent of the People themſelves, Joſhuah 1. 18. <note place="margin">Joſ. 1. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>Whoſoever he be that doth Rebel againſt thy Commandment and will not hearken to thy words in all that thou commandeſt him, ſhall be put to death.</hi> Here is no exception of Perſons, the Law being gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and comprehenſive. I might enforce this argument by all thoſe Titles wherewith Kings are dignified in the Old Teſtament, <note place="margin">2 Sam. 21. 17. Lament. 4. 20. 2 Sam. 14. 19. 1 Sam. 15. 20.</note> Of the <hi>lights of Iſrael,</hi> The <hi>breath</hi> of <hi>their Noſtrils,</hi> The <hi>Angels of God,</hi> and The <hi>Heads of the People;</hi> All which ſpeak them ſupream and invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olable. I might alſo tell you what care God took, to ſecure them from any violent attempts by reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mens hearts as well as tongues, by forbidding
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96812:9"/> them not only publickly to revile, <note place="margin">Exod. 22. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>. Eccleſ. 10. 20.</note> but ſo much as to <hi>curſe</hi> them in <hi>thought,</hi> leſt a <hi>bird of the ayre</hi> (An Angel of God) might <hi>tell the matter;</hi> much leſs might the hand be lifted up againſt them, <hi>For who can ſtretch forth his hand againſt the Lords Anointed and be guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs?</hi> ſays <hi>David,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26. 9. <note place="margin">1 Sam. 26. 9.</note> If any might have done it, then He to be ſure, as next heir to the Crown, declared ſo by God himſelf, and already Anointed to it, and who might now have made way for himſelf to it by diſpatching <hi>Saul</hi> who was then in his hand; and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity and Providence (our late great Pleas and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences) might ſeem to have led him to it: But ſo far was <hi>David</hi> from doing him any hurt himſelf, that he would not ſuffer thoſe whoſe fingers itcht to be doing, and who came with a <hi>dixit Dominus</hi> in their mouths, to injure him in the leaſt; would not give way to his own Paſſion or his Souldiers ſolicitation. The only uſe he makes of it is the tryal of his Patience and the means of his Peace. <hi>David</hi> might as eaſily have cut off <hi>Saul</hi>'s head as his garment; but his Coat only ſhall be the worſe for it, not his Perſon. Like <hi>Aaron's pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Ointment</hi> he deſcends only to <hi>the skirts of his Cloathing;</hi> nor ſhould his garment have been maim'd for a revenge, but only for a monument of his Innocency. And yet as not well ſecured of that, the leaſt rent of that garment tears his heart worſe, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25. 5. <note place="margin">2 Sam. 25. 5.</note> Now what was it that ſo becalm'd and ſmooth'd his own and his Followers Paſſion but the Holy Oyle that was on <hi>Saul</hi>'s head? <hi>Timuit Oleum,</hi> ſayes <hi>Optatus; Saul</hi> was the Lords Anointed, That was charm enough to tye up <hi>David</hi>'s hand.</p>
                  <p>Nor do we find that the Jewiſh Nation did ever pretend to bring any of their moſt extravagant Kings into order either by way of force or Juſtice, but left them to ſtand or fall to their own Maſter, whenever they did ſuch things as were puniſhable by the Law
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96812:10"/> of <hi>Moſes.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Exod. 22. 20.</note> By which Law though every Idolater was to dye without mercy, yet where do we find that <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes</hi> (An Idolater and a cruel Tyrant to boot) was ever puniſht for it by the People? Or where do we learn that <hi>Elias</hi> (A man of a fiery ſpirit, and zealous for his God) did call down fire from Heaven to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume a wicked <hi>Ahab</hi> as he did his Captains of fifties and their Bands? When <hi>David</hi> had committed Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery (which was mortal too by the Law of <hi>Moſes, Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit.</hi> 20. 10.) <note place="margin">Levit. 20. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>Nathan</hi> brings no Authority from the People to puniſh, he only threatens him from God, cites him to his Tribunal, and <hi>David</hi> himſelf well knew he was to ſtand at no other barr, <note place="margin">Pſal. 51. 4.</note> his <hi>Tibi ſoli peccavi,</hi> ſecures him from man's; and St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi>'s Comment on theſe words puts it out of Queſtion, <hi>Rex erat;</hi> He was a King, and that was his Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rex uti<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> erat, nullis Ipſe le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus teneba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, quia li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beri ſunt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges à vinculis delictorum.</hi> St. Ambr. Apolog. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid. c. 10.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>But though the People had no Authority over their Prince, had not the High Prieſt? Jeſuites in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſay ſo, but without any ground at all. For they cannot ſhew us any one ſingle act of Juriſdiction exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed by the High Prieſt over the King, whereas we can of the Kings over him; <note place="margin">1 King. 2. 26, 27.</note> of a <hi>Solomon</hi> on an <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>athar.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2 Chron. 26.</note> That which they urge here of <hi>Azariah</hi>'s thruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out <hi>Uzziah</hi> out of the Temple, is nothing to the purpoſe. That was no act of violence againſt him for burning Incenſe to the Lord, and ſo ſeizing on the Prieſts Office, as is pretended, much leſs any depriving him of his Regal Authority (which he enjoyed while he lived.) <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jud. Antiq. lib.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 11. See 2 Chron. 26. 20.</note> But, as <hi>Joſephus</hi> informs us, an Advice or Admonition to him to depart haſtily out of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, God having ſmitten him with Leproſie, and all Lepers being to dwell without the Camp, according to the Levitical Law, <hi>Levit.</hi> 13. 46. <note place="margin">Levit. 13. 46. 2 King. 11.</note> Nor is that other inſtance of <hi>Jehoiada</hi>'s ſlaying <hi>Athalia,</hi> any whit more pertinent. For <hi>Jehoiada,</hi> (who had for ſome years ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:96812:10"/> 
                     <hi>Joas</hi> in the Temple from the fury of that Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs) being Unkle and Protector to <hi>Joas</hi> in his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nority, did, with the conſent of the chief of the Realm, only declare him King, who was ſo before, as by Right of ſucceſſion, ſo by Gods own ſpecial appointment, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 23. 3. <note place="margin">2 Chron. 23. 3.</note> Nor did he cauſe <hi>Athalia</hi> to be ſlain, till <hi>Joas</hi> had been ſeated on his Royal Throne, <hi>v.</hi> 11. <note place="margin">v. 11.</note> ſo that 'twas not ſo much His as <hi>Joas</hi>'s Act, in whoſe name and by whoſe Authority He cauſed it to be done. Here then was no act of the High Prieſts Juriſdiction over the King; nor can it be made appear that ever the <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> (The Higheſt Court of Judicature among the Jews, and who had Authority to puniſh Falſe Prophets with death) <note place="margin">Deut. 13. 5.</note> did ever pretend a power of puniſhing Princes ſo. After the Babyloniſh Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity indeed nothing was done without their Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Joſeph. Ant. Jud. lib.</hi> 14. <hi>c.</hi> 17.</note> Then we read that <hi>Herod</hi> was cited to appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them to anſwer for ſome miſdemeanours he had committed, He being but a private Perſon, his Father <hi>Antipater</hi> alive, and <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> then reigning. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>To.</hi> 1. <hi>Annal. ad An. Chriſti</hi> 31. <hi>num.</hi> 10. <hi>Exercitat. lib.</hi> 13. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> So falſe is it what <hi>Baronius</hi> confidently affirms, That all Kings were obnoxious to the Judgement of the <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> as <hi>Caſaubon</hi> ſhews. Only this muſt be confeſt, That Kingly power, toward the end of the Jewiſh Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, was much reſtrained by the Senare; ſo that what <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſayes of the Kingdom of <hi>Lacedaemonia,</hi> is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable to that of <hi>Judaea</hi> in thoſe times, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ar. Pol. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</note> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, That Kings could not do all then as once they could when their Power was Abſolute, and when by the judgement of the beſt Jewiſh Doctors, it was utterly unlawful to call them to an Account; witneſs that ſaying of theirs, cited out of their <hi>Talmud, Rex nec judicat nec judicatur;</hi> which as it was falſe as to the former part of it (as 'tis evident from 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. 5. <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8 5.</note> where the People deſire a King that might judge them like <hi>all the Nations,</hi> and what kind of Kings thoſe were
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:96812:11"/> I have already ſhewn you) ſo was it moſt true as to the latter branch of it, That He was not to be judged of any. A piece of Divinity ſo generally owned and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by the Jews, that it became a Proverbial ſaying with them, <hi>Nulla creatura judicat Regem, ſed Deus Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That this was the doctrine of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, made good by the example of Holy men, and avowed by the ableſt and ſoundeſt Jewiſh Doctors, Theſe Chief Prieſts here could not be ignorant of, as men who had been trained up in the Schools of the Prophets and in all likelyhood well verſt in their own Hiſtories and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices. And therefore to avoid the force of <hi>Pilates</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, they own his Reaſon but deny his ſuppoſition, That Chriſt was their King, <hi>We have no King but Caeſar.</hi> My ſecond general Part.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>The ſecond Part.</head>
               <p>'Twas impoſſible in ſo few words to expreſs more flattery, ſhall I ſay, Blaſphemy or Folly. Here is hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie in the height, in owning <hi>Caeſar</hi> for their King. He was ſo indeed, but ſore againſt their wills; <note place="margin">See Deut. 17. 15.</note> one whom Conqueſt had forced upon them, and whom they mortally hated as an Uſurper, an Enemy to their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Cuſtomes. Nor was it poſſible for them to love him, while they held it no better than a ſinful Vaſſalage to ſtoop to a Heathen Scepter; A fancy <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das Gaulonites</hi> and <hi>Saducus</hi> had put into their heads. Thus they how their knee to <hi>Caeſar</hi> as they did to Chriſt, with a <hi>Hail King of the Jews;</hi> proclaiming him with their mouths but not with their hearts, <hi>Aut Caeſar aut nullus, Caeſar</hi> muſt be their King.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:96812:11"/>
               <p>And why not Chriſt? was it not becauſe there was no King in <hi>Zion?</hi> did not theſe men look for a <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah?</hi> And was not this the proper time to expect him, when according to <hi>Jacobs</hi> Prophecy, <note place="margin">Gen. 49. 10.</note> the Scepter was departed from <hi>Juda?</hi> Had not malice and envy blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their eyes, they might eaſily have known him by all thoſe marks their Prophets gave them of the Meſſiah, and which were ſo viſible on him. Nor was it long before that themſelves would have made him their King, that they followed him in Triumph into <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> with <hi>Hoſanna</hi>'s to this Son of <hi>David</hi> as loud as now their Crucifiges; <note place="margin">Joh. 6. 15.</note> and is the note ſo ſoon chang'd? How much better <hi>Pilate,</hi> a Heathen, than they who both owned him here for their King, and a little after proclaimed him ſuch by a publick Inſcription on his Croſs? Yet <hi>Nolumus hunc,</hi> is their language, and by rejecting Chriſt what did they but renounce all hope of a deliverer? This was their extream Folly and they ſoon ſmarted for it, when Chriſt's light yoke was turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into an iron one that galled their necks to purpoſe; when the ſeditious practices of the furious Zealots lured the Roman Eagles to their Carkaſſes, according to the literal meaning of our Lords prediction, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. 28. <note place="margin">Matth. 24. 28.</note> Thus for their refuſing Chriſt and chooſing <hi>Caeſar</hi> for their Lord, 'twas juſt with God to plague them by that <hi>Caeſar;</hi> That they who rejected the mild Empire of a Lamb, ſhould have a devouring Stork ſet over them, and the <hi>Venient Romani,</hi> once their Fear, ſhould at laſt prove their judgement.<note place="margin">Joh. 11. 48.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But beſides this, there is a great abſurdity in their anſwer here to <hi>Pilate,</hi> an oppoſition implyed between Chriſt and <hi>Caeſar.</hi> They ſay Chriſt is not their King becauſe <hi>Caeſar</hi> is. The Anabaptiſt and the Jew are here ſo croſs, that 'tis ſtrange one <hi>Amſterdam</hi> ſhould hold them both. The one ſayes, Chriſt is our King,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96812:12"/> and therefore not <hi>Caeſar;</hi> The other, <hi>Caeſar</hi> is our King, and therefore not Chriſt; as if theſe two, Chriſt and <hi>Caeſar</hi> were incompatible. 'Twas this miſtake that rais'd all the Plots againſt our Saviour; This, that awakened <hi>Herod</hi>'s jealouſie, and provok't his rage, when he heard of a <hi>King of the Jews.</hi> But his fears were as needleſs, as they were pernicious; ſince He, who gave all Earthly Monarchs their Crowns, did not come with any deſign to pluck them off their heads. The not well underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a due ſubordination between Chriſts and <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Kingdom, is that which has ſpilt ſo much blood in the World. There may be danger in contrariety, but in diverſity there is none. 'Twas a blaſphemous inconſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence then in theſe Chief Prieſts, <hi>Caeſar</hi> is our King, therefore not Chriſt; whereas they ſhould rather have argued thus, Yea, rather <hi>Caeſar,</hi> becauſe Chriſt, it being not neceſſary that Religion and Policy ſhould claſh, nor at all impoſſible to <hi>Render unto</hi> Caeſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Caeſar<hi>'s,</hi> and yet not deny <hi>God the things that are God's.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We have had, and ſtill have ſuch loud cryes as theſe among us too; Of ſome, who will have no King but Him that wears the Triple Crown, all the reſt muſt hold theirs precariouſly from Him. Of others, who are for a King <hi>Jeſus,</hi> owning Him indeed for their King, but in as bad a ſenſe as theſe here diſclaim'd him. The diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between theſe two is not very great. The One would have blown up their King, and the Other did actually cut off his head. Their Impiety was much alike, but not their Modeſty: The former being content to contrive his deſtruction in a Cave, while the other had the impudence to murder him on a Scaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold. A third ſort of People we have ſeen too; who were for a Monarch with theſe <hi>Jews,</hi> but one of their own ſetting up: For any thing rather than the True
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:96812:12"/> One; For a Traytor and a Murderer; a <hi>Barabbas</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a <hi>Chriſtus Domini,</hi> a Bramble for a Cedar. The Chief Prieſts of thoſe times were mainly for ſuch a one (If they were Prieſts at all, for 'tis queſtionable whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther many of them were; nay, 'tis certain that ſome of them were not, and that All of them were at beſt but <hi>Jeroboam</hi>'s Prieſts, <hi>of the meaneſt of the People).</hi> We know whom theſe men would once have had for their King, <hi>Jeroboam</hi> was to be the Man, One for all Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons but the right one; As good a Prieſt himſelf as they that would have ſet him up, who carryed a Sword in one hand, and a Cenſer in the other; One that ſet up his <hi>Calves</hi> in oppoſition to the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when he ſaw he was not for his turn; A <hi>Phocas</hi> who by the murder of his Lord aſpir'd to the Diadem, and he miſt it narrowly, the Power he had already got into his hands, but God would not ſuffer him to enjoy the Title, and not long after ſtript him and his ridiculous Succeſſor of all their Theatrical Pomp, making them give way to the True <hi>Caeſar.</hi> And bleſſed be God that we can truly ſay what theſe <hi>Jews</hi> here ſpake falſly, <hi>We have</hi> Caeſar <hi>for our King.</hi> Let us then give him thoſe things that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long unto Him, that which our Religion commands us to pay Him. And what that is, is to be our third and laſt Enquiry.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>The Third Part.<note place="margin" type="runSum">The Doctrine and Practice of Chriſt, his Apoſtles and Primitive Fathers.</note>
               </head>
               <p>That all Magiſtracy is from God, we learn from Rom. 13. 1. <hi>The Powers that be, are ordained of God;</hi> and that all degrees and orders of men are from Him, is as evident. For God never deſign'd ſuch a Parity as ſome men dream of. A thing, as contrary to Nature, ſo to all Reaſon and Religion. What is commonly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:96812:13"/> ſaid, That all men are born Equal, that Innocence knew no Superiour but God, and that ſubjection came in with ſin; is ſpeciouſly, but very falſly alledg'd. That Slave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry came in with ſin, I grant, not Civil ſubjection. As there was at firſt a plain diſtinction and inequality be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Father and Son; ſo the different gifts of men im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it; ſome being born with ſuch Heroick Spirits, as if deſign'd by God to govern others, whoſe ſtronger abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of body than of mind, ſeem to have fitted them only for ſubjection. This the Philoſopher ſeems to make the ground of all Civil Government, <hi>Polit.</hi> 1. And indeed without ſuch an Inequality there could be None. For every man ſtanding in a Ring or Circle, where the roundneſs takes away all diſtinction, none can be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore or after another; Every ſingle perſon ſhall then be a Monarch and a Subject, as 'twas in that <hi>Cyclopedian</hi> Anarchy deſcrib'd by <hi>Euripides,</hi> which the Levelling Doctrine does inevitably introduce, as againſt all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſo againſt the very intereſt of the Deſigners them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Againſt Reaſon, as a thing utterly impracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable; To reduce all men to the ſame pitch of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being as unreaſonable a Tyranny as was that of <hi>Procruſtes,</hi> who would fit all Bodies to one bed. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the intereſt of the Deſigners too, who would have all equal indeed beſides themſelves; and I may add, Againſt Religion; For Chriſt allows no ſuch thing, and thoſe <hi>Higher Powers</hi> mention'd by St. <hi>Paul</hi> clearly imply a diſtinction. And who thoſe <hi>Higher Powers</hi> were, the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in the ſame Verſe declare, The Powers then in being, which can be underſtood of none but the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours. Theſe were then the <hi>Higheſt Powers</hi> on Earth; To theſe St. <hi>Peter</hi> commands ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection as to the <hi>Supream,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 13. <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 13.</note> Theſe, as our Lord tells us, did <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <note place="margin">Matth. 20. 25. 2 Cor. 1. 24.</note> that is, as the words import, exerciſe ſuch an abſolute and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream authority over men, as Maſters have over their
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:96812:13"/> Servants, and Lords over their Vaſſals. And ſo far was Chriſt from diſputing them this their juſt Authority, <note place="margin">Matth. 17. 27.</note> that He not only paid them Tribute in token of his own ſubjection (though not without the expence of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle) but expreſly commands all his to do ſo; <note place="margin">22. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Render unto Caeſar,</hi> the word there is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Reſtore to Him his due, as if it were not ſo much a Gift as a Debt. Thus did our Lord, and thus did his Apoſtles teach us; Nor do we find that any of the Primitive Fathers taught otherwiſe than to own Kings as ſupream, and depending only upon God. 'Tis a known ſaying that of <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ad Scapulam.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Colimus Imperatorem ut hominem à Deo ſecundum &amp; ſolo Deo minorem;</hi> and that of <hi>Optatus</hi> to the like purpoſe; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Adverſus Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. lib.</hi> 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Supra Imperatorem non eſt niſi Deus qui fecit Imperatorem.</hi> I ſhould be infinite, if I ſhould cite Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to this purpoſe, and I think it needleſs, it being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for any to produced one ſingle paſſage out of the Antient Fathers to the contrary.</p>
               <p>That which ſome object out of 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 13. <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 13.</note> That Kings are but <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>an Ordinance of Man;</hi> ſignifies no more than this, That Kingly Government, as all other, is exerciſed by men, and deſign'd for the good of humane ſociety; not that it is not of a Divine Inſtitution: For the very word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> there recalls us to God as to its Author, and in the very ſame Verſe we find it rais'd to a divine workmanſhip, <hi>Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of man for the Lords ſake.</hi> Who as he is called <hi>the Ordinance of man</hi> by St. <hi>Peter;</hi> ſo is he expreſly ſtyl'd <hi>the Ordinance of God,</hi> by St. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 13. 2.</p>
               <p>But then ſecondly, May not the Prieſt now under the Goſpel claim a Superiority over Princes? St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſayes nothing to countenance that claim, (he ſtrongly implyes the contrary in the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 13.</note> but his pretended Succeſſor will by all means have it ſo, <note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>He who exalteth himſelf above all that is called God,</hi> to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96812:14"/> whoſe Mitre all Crowns muſt vail, and that by virtue of a <hi>Dabo tibi Claves,</hi> which Keys he can eaſily turn into a Sword as oft as he finds occaſion to imploy it againſt Soveraign Princes, and then any pretence ſhall warrant the uſe of it. <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſayes <hi>Aquinas,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Comment. in</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 9. Exod. 19. 6. 1 Pet. 2. 9.</note> ſtyles the <hi>Jews</hi> a <hi>Prieſtly Kingdom,</hi> Exod. 19. 6. And St. <hi>Peter</hi> us Chriſtians a <hi>Kingly Prieſthood,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 9. and from thence he ſtrongly concludes, that as Judaiſm did ſtand through the Kings ſuperiority over Prieſts: (which is more by the bye than what <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and his Aſſociates will grant him) ſo Chriſtianity through the Prieſts ſuperiority over Kings. An argument much like that once made uſe of to prove the Pope to be above the Emperour, becauſe 'tis ſaid, <note place="margin">Gen. 1. 16.</note> That God made a <hi>Greater light to rule the day, and a leſſer to rule the night.</hi> But to this I ſhall oppoſe St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s practice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and precept. His practice we have clear, <hi>Acts</hi> 25. 11. <note place="margin">Acts 25. 10, 11.</note> where he appeals to <hi>Caeſar</hi> as to the higheſt Judge on Earth, where he ſayes he <hi>ought to be judged;</hi> and that, as 'tis very obſervable, in a matter of ſpiritual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, as it will plainly appear, by comparing <hi>v.</hi> 19. here with the ſixth Verſe of <hi>Chap.</hi> 23. <note place="margin">v. 19. Chap. 23. 6.</note> where he tells us that <hi>Of the hope and Reſurrection of the dead he was called in queſtion.</hi> This was his practice; and he did no more than what he commands all men to do, to be <hi>ſubject to the Higher Power,</hi> that is, to that very <hi>Roman</hi> Emperour to whom he appeals, and his <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Every Soul</hi> includes all, whether Apoſtle, Evangeliſt or Prophet, in the Judgement of far better and more Authentick Interpreters than any of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts,</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hom.</hi> 23. <hi>in Rom.</hi>
                  </note> St. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> 
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>In locum. Si omnis Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, etiam ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra. Quis vos excepit ab U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſitate? Qui tentat ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipere, conatur decipere.</hi> Bernard. ad Henr. Senones f. 1. Ep. 42. Greg. M. lib. 2. Epiſt. ad Mauritium 72. Et ad Theodoric. Reg. Fancorum lib. 9. Epiſt. 53.</note> 
                  <hi>Theodoret, Theophy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lact, Oecumenius</hi> and even St. <hi>Bernard</hi> too. To which I ſhall add the practice of <hi>Gregory the Great,</hi> himſelf a Pope, but much more mannerly than his ſucceſſors,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:96812:14"/> whoſe humble Addreſſes to <hi>Mauritius</hi> the Emperour, whom he ſtyles his Lord, as alſo to <hi>Theodoric</hi> King of the <hi>Franks</hi> whom he beſeeches to call a Synod, plainly ſhew, how little he then dreamt of ſtanding in compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition with his Prince. A ſubmiſſion his Succeſſours can no more reliſh now than his diſclaiming the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Monarchy. And we know what a quarrel there was like to have been in this latter age between <hi>Paul</hi> 5. and the Republick of <hi>Venice,</hi> partly upon this account, that They would not ſuffer ſome <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Non poſſunt Clerici à Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice ſaeculari judicari, eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amſi leges ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viles non ſervent.</hi> Bell. de Clericis, lib. 1. c. 38. <hi>Rebellio Clerici adverſus Principem, non eſt crimen laeſae Majeſtatis, quia Principi non eſt ſubditus.</hi> Em. Sa Aphor. Tit. Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus.</note> Religious Perſons to have leave to violate all the Laws of God and of that State.</p>
               <p>And here 'tis ſtrange to ſee how lovingly Jeſuites and Sectaries agree together to dethrone and murder the <hi>Lords Anointed:</hi> How like <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s Foxes they carry fire in their tayles while their heads ſeem to point divers wayes. <hi>Nemo tam prope tam procul<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>—</hi>Their Principles and practices much alike. That the Prince was made for the People; <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>In Rebus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publicis Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralibus ſi Rex degeneret in Tyrannum, licet caput ſit regni, tamen à populo poteſt deponi &amp; eligi alius.</hi> Bell. de Concil. lib. 2. c. 19. &amp; Recogn. lib. de laicis ſect. <hi>Addo experientiam; Laudat Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varrum qui non dubitat affirmare, Nunquam Populum ita poteſtatem ſuam in Regem transferre, quin illam ſibi in habitu retineat, ut in certis quibuſdam caſibus etiam actu recipere poſſit.</hi>
                  </note> That the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple can never ſo far transferr their power over to a King but that they retain the habit of it ſtill within themſelves, and may in ſome caſes actually reaſſume it; <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Poteſtas immediate eſt tanquam in ſubjecto in totâ multitudine, &amp; ſi cauſa legitima adſit, poteſt multitudo mutare regnum in Ariſtocratiam, aut Democratiam, &amp; è contra, ut Romae factum legimus.</hi> Bell. de Laicis lib. 3. c. 6.</note> That when Kings tranſgreſs Laws they become ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to the Penalties of them, and may be <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Verum principem, qui Tyrannus eſt ratione adminiſtrationis, non poſſe à privatis inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imi quamdiu manet Princeps—primùm à Republ. vel Comitiis Regni, vel alio habente au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritatem, eſſe deponendum, ut in ipſius Perſonam liceat quicquam attentare.</hi> Leſſius. lib. 2. de Juſtit. &amp; Jure c. 9. dubio 4.</note> depoſed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:96812:15"/> and killed by the People; That we are to diſtinguiſh between their Perſons and their Authority, and may with a ſafe Conſcience oppoſe the former, though not the latter; And, to ſumm up all in one, That <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Domina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio Temporalis &amp; ſuperioritas in ſubditos per ſententiam Papae poteſt omnino adimi Haereticis.</hi> Greg. de Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent. To. 3. diſp. in Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam. Diſ. 1. qu. 12. p. 2.</note> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion is founded in Grace, Bad Kings have no right to their Crown<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor bad men to any of Gods Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. All theſe doctrines are delivered by the Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites either expreſly or at leaſt implicitely; and ſince they firſt give the premiſes, whereof ſuch rebellious concluſions are the clear and natural iſſues, 'tis eaſie to ſee to whom our late Pamphleteers are beholding for their Deſtructive Principles, and that they have whet thoſe Swords, wherewith they have cut off the head of their Prince, at the forges of theſe Philiſtines.</p>
               <p>But we <hi>have not ſo learned Chriſt.</hi> He never taught us to diſtinguiſh between the Perſon and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of a Prince, no more than St. <hi>Paul</hi> did when he bad us be <hi>ſubject to the Higher Powers.</hi> A nicety coyned by Rebellious heads, but which never came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that of this Holy Apoſtle, who only conformed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the Roman ſtyle, with whom 'twas ordinary to call Perſons <hi>Poteſtates</hi> in the Abſtract. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>An Fidenatum Gabiorumve eſſe Poteſtas.</hi> Juv. Sat. 10. v. Epheſ. 3. 10.</note> And therefore <hi>v.</hi> 3. The ſame Perſons are ſtiled <hi>Rulers</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <hi>v.</hi> 6. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Miniſters</hi> in the Maſculine, who <hi>v.</hi> 1. were entituled <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Powers;</hi> to let us know, That every affront to their Perſons is ſin becauſe of their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</p>
               <p>But then ſecondly, That Dominion is founded in Grace, ſo that Subjects may be free to caſt off the Royal yoke, in caſe a Prince will not, or they at leaſt perſwade themſelves, He does not, ſubmit his neck to Chriſts, is the very Root of all Rebellion; A maxime, which not only turns Kings out of their Thrones, but all Men out of their Poſſeſſions, who have not the mark of their Election viſible on their foreheads. A Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which has ſhed more blood than now runs in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:96812:15"/> the veins of living Chriſtians, and is that which in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect did Murder our late Soveraign. That Religion, Grace or Vertue gives Princes a Right to Govern, is as falſe as it is pernicious. Their Right to Govern is annexed to their Soveraignty, nor are their Perſons Sacred in relation to their Divine or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ral endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but in regard of Empire. For <hi>Cyrus</hi> was <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus Domini</hi> as well as <hi>Joſias,</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> as well as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 45. 1, 5.</note> If Religion made Kings, then ſhould there of old have been no true Kings but thoſe of <hi>Juda,</hi> nor any now but thoſe of Chriſtendom. St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Saul,</hi> ſays, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Non habebat innocentiam &amp; tamen habebat ſanctitatem.</hi> Auguſt. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Lit. Petil. l. 2. c. 48.</note> He had not Innocence but he had Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, not of Life, but of Unction. This made <hi>David</hi> ſo revere him when alive, and ſo ſeverely puniſh him, when dead, by cauſing the <hi>Amalekite</hi> to be ſlain for but falſly reporting himſelf his Executioner. The errours or miſdemeanours of Kings can no more diſanul their Authority, than <hi>man's Unbelief can make void the faith of God.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 3. 3.</note> 'Tis not every ſailing of the husband that can yield his Wife a juſt cauſe for a ſeparation, ſhe muſt Take him for better or for worſe. The King is the <hi>Head</hi> of his Subjects, as the Husband is the <hi>Head</hi> of his <hi>Wife;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 15. 17. 1 Cor. 11. 3.</note> He ſolemnly weds himſelf to his people at his Coronation, and his Oath there makes the match; But what if he break his Oath, ſhall his Perjury to God make him loſe his juſt Authority over men? or releaſe his Subjects of their duty? This is the Sectarian and Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitical doctrine; <hi>Buchanan</hi> and <hi>Emanuel Sa</hi> both aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure us, <note place="margin">Buchan. de jur. regni p. 53. in 8. Eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg. 1581. Eman. Sa A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor. Tit. Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannus.</note> That in ſuch a caſe 'tis lawful for any man to take away the Life of a Tyrant, that is, ſuch a one as they fancy to be ſo. A piece of Divinity borrowed from <hi>Tully</hi> who had ſaid the ſame thing many Ages be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, but warranted by no Scripture or practice of any Primitive Chriſtians. Theſe all owned and ſubmitted themſelves to Tyrannical Princes. What was the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:96812:16"/> Emperour in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s time but ſuch, and does He in the leaſt queſtion his Authority? Does he not call Him <hi>The Ordinance of God?</hi> Does he not preach ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to Him and that <hi>not for fear but for Conſcience?</hi> Did his Tyranny or wickedneſs waſh off that holy oyle wherewith <hi>God had anointed him above his fellows?</hi> And what his Infidelity and Cruelty to boot, could not do then, ſhall Hereſie be able to do now? Could ſuch faults dethrone Princes, not many of them perhaps would heretofore have ſate faſt on their Thrones. <hi>Conſtantius, Valens, Valentinianus,</hi> Arrians all, yet were never thought leſs Emperours for all that. <hi>Julian</hi> more, an Apoſtate, yet dyed a Prince. But, <hi>Vires deerant,</hi> Their Subjects then wanted power to call them to an account. <hi>Tertullian</hi> has furniſht me with an anſwer; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apologet. c.</hi> 37.</note> That Chriſtians then filled all places, Towns, Camp and even the Court it ſelf. Beſides, The <hi>Theban</hi> Legion, who choſe rather to be Martyrs than Rebels, are a pregnant inſtance to the contrary. Men that durſt look any thing in the face but Majeſty, That could ſtand before any Enemy but not before their Soveraign except to wait his Commands. Here only their courage failed them; They could ſuffer their own blood to be ſhed, but knew not our late art of Phle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>botomy, of letting out their Princes heart blood. That Arch-Rebel among us, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job. Goodwin. Anti-Caval.</hi>
                  </note> who with his brother <hi>Mariana</hi> the Jeſuite has written a Book in defence of Regicide, not knowing what to ſay to ſo plain an Inſtance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes himſelf to this pretty Fanatical ſhift: That that honeſt liberty of King-killing was hid from ſome Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians for ſome ſpecial ends, which God hath ſince revealed to this latter age; That ſuch an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary patience and paſſive courage were neceſſary in thoſe dayes, which are inconvenient in ours, wherein more plentiful light has made us ſee it expedient rather
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:96812:16"/> to be Aſſaſſines than Martyrs. 'Tis now the wicked's turn to ſuffer, and Antichriſt cannot be deſtroyed except thoſe Kings be, which yet the Scripture expreſly tells us are the very Perſons that ſhall pull him down, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. 16. <note place="margin">Revel. 17. 16.</note> Thus are we, in a buſineſs of ſuch high moment, to be guided by obſcure fanatical conjectures rather than by thoſe plain precepts of Loyalty and ſubjection the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture gives us, and <hi>the man of Sin</hi> cannot down with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out our ſin too. This is the excellent and ſafe doctrine of Sectaries; This, their Chriſtian liberty, to ſhake off that yoke to Princes which Chriſt has bound ſo faſt to their necks, and is now become ſo great a part of his own. He who has commanded ſervants to obey even <hi>froward</hi> Maſters, and Children harſh and unnatural Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 18.</note> has enjoyned ſubjects as ſtrict an obedience to Tyrannical Princes. What Law is there for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to call his Maſter to an account, or the Child his Father? Or where have we any precept or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample in Scripture for queſtioning Soveraign Princes? Will theſe Saints challenge to themſelves a greater Authority than Chriſt ever took upon him? Where do we find that he exerciſed any Juriſdiction on the Powers then in being? He who refuſed to be made a <hi>Judge</hi> between private parties? <note place="margin">Luk. 12. 14.</note> Will theſe New Saints pretend to judge the World now, becauſe Gods Saints ſhall <hi>judge</hi> it hereafter? <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6. 2.</note> Chriſt indeed tells his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles that <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>They</hi> ſhould be <hi>brought before Kings and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours,</hi> but no where that <hi>Kings and Governours</hi> ſhould be brought before Them to receive their doom; much leſs, before the People, or their Repreſentatives either, ſince They can give Theſe no greater a power than themſelves had, nor ſuch a power to be ſure as they have once paſt away. That diſtinction of <hi>Singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis Major &amp; Univerſis Minor,</hi> coyned in the Conſiſtory and Claſſis, we find no where in Scripture. There we hear of a <hi>King</hi> as <hi>Supream,</hi> and of inferiour <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:96812:17"/> 
                  <hi>ſent</hi> and impowred <hi>by Him,</hi> but nothing of their being above Him that ſent them, put them all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. There we hear that the Higheſt Power is the <hi>Miniſter of God,</hi> not of the People; <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 4.</note> and his <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to execute wrath</hi> on others, not to be ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the terrible effects of anothers wrath. There we are told, that God has put the <hi>Sword</hi> into his, not any others hand, That all beſides Him do <hi>Take,</hi> uſurp it, and <hi>ſhall</hi> therefore <hi>Periſh with it, Matth.</hi> 26. 52. <note place="margin">Matth. 26. 52.</note> Much more they who employ it to His deſtruction, who has the only right to uſe it. We are commanded there to <hi>Pray for Kings,</hi> not to murder them; <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 2.</note> To lift up our hands to God For, not againſt them; To <hi>ſubmit</hi> to the Worſt, not to trample on the Beſt of them; <hi>To bind Kings in Chains,</hi> and then Behead them, is an <hi>honour</hi> peculiar to the <hi>Saints</hi> of this Age, not Chriſt's. Calling a King to an account was the Brat of Pope <hi>Hildebrand</hi>'s brain. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>V. Platin. in vitâ Greg.</hi> 7.</note> Jeſuits and Sectaries have broacht and practiſed it. Our Kalendar preſents us with a Fifth of <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> as well as a Thirtieth of <hi>January.</hi> No Goſpel for this, but the <hi>Evangelium Armatum:</hi> It ſuits well with the <hi>Turkiſh Alchoran</hi> and the practice of <hi>Janiza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> to make and unmake their Emperour in a day. Chriſt bids his Followers <hi>cut off their right hand when it offends</hi> them, not their Soveraign's head, when they but fancy Him offenſive. A Doctrine good Chriſtians have ever abhorr'd, The worſt of <hi>Jews</hi> we ſee were aſham'd of; nay, the worſt of Heathens too utterly diſclaim'd; And yet Chriſtians, and they who would be thought the Beſt, nay, the only true Chriſtians, have allowed, practiſed and maintain'd.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Applic.</hi>
                  </note> But Chriſtians of another make and temper than here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, till new lights were hung up; Chriſtians who tell us, That a King may be arraign'd, ſentenced and put to death by his People when he fails of his duty, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:96812:17"/> themſelves to be Judges of his failings. A Doctrine, which if in it ſelf true (as it's moſt falſe) would prove here of no other uſe, but to condemn the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors and Abettors of it, ſince 'twas moſt wrongly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd by them to One, in whom there were no ſuch Uſurpation, Tyranny, Wickedneſs, or Weakneſs, as was pretended. For</p>
               <p n="1">1. Here was as Lawful a King as God and Nature, Law and the Subjects Oaths, could render Him. Here was <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a King <hi>Born,</hi> whom neither Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes nor Election had made ſuch. A King by Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion (the beſt Title now that any can have to a Crown) No Muſhrome one, ſprung up in a night, but the <hi>Son of Nobles,</hi> the blood of ſo many Royal Veins running in his; one own'd for ſuch even by thoſe that crucify'd Him, in their Inſcription of, <hi>Regum Ultimus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. A good, pious Chriſtian and Proteſtant King. Too good for ſo ungrateful a People. A People whom He had even loaded and tyred out with his gracious Conceſſions; that <hi>clothed them</hi> as <hi>Saul</hi> did <hi>Jeruſalem, in Scarlet with other delights,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 1. 24.</note> brought Peace and Plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Wealth and Propriety, Honour and Security, to the Nation, every man ſafely and quietly <hi>ſitting under his own Vine and Fig-tree. A nurſing Father</hi> alſo to the Church, under whoſe happy ſhelter and Protection it flouriſhed to the admiration and envy of all round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout us; A Church, which (as <hi>Auguſtus</hi> is ſaid to have done to <hi>Rome)</hi> He chang'd from Brick to Marble, reforming its manners as much by His own Royal Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, as He did its Structure by His Bounty and Muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence. Well might He ſay with His Saviour, <note place="margin">John 10. 32.</note> 
                  <hi>Many good works have I ſhewn you, for which of thoſe works do ye ſtone me?</hi> Had He made His Will the Rule of His Government, and that Will revealed it ſelf in twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years of injuſtice; Had He worn a Table-Book in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:96812:18"/> His Pocket with the Names of the Nobility markt in it for ſlaughter; Had He without any Tryal at Law made His Pleaſure paſs for Sentence, and lop't off Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors heads as faſt as <hi>Tarquin</hi> did <hi>Poppy</hi>'s; Had He in His Oppreſſions of the People made them feel Times ſuch as <hi>Tacitus</hi> deſcribes, where no man durſt be virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, leſt he ſhould be thought to upbraid his Prince, and where not only mens Words, but their Looks and Sighs were proſcrib'd. In a word, Had He with <hi>Caligula,</hi> wiſh't His Kingdom one head, that He might ſtrike it off at a blow; The Rebellious Principles of his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries might have given them ſome colourable pretence to cut off His, and He might then ſeem to have deſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that Title, which their Charity after His death be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon Him, of <hi>Tyrannorum Maximus.</hi> But there was nothing of all this in the caſe; Here was an Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, Juſt, Virtuous and Religious King, in whom 'tis hard to ſay, which was moſt eminent, His Piety to God, or His Love to His ſubjects; to whom He liv'd a Father, and for whom He dyed a Martyr.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A Wiſe and Able King, whoſe endowments of mind were anſwerable to His Virtues, rendring Him worthy of that Scepter He was born to. <hi>In uno hoc Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſare multi Marii.</hi> Thoſe ſeveral perfections ſcattered in others, all concentred in this Excellent Prince. That Kings have larger <hi>hearts</hi> and abilities than ordinary men, we learn from 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. 9. <note place="margin">Sam. 10. 9.</note> That this King had, His moſt implacable Enemies have, to their own ſhame, often acknowledged.</p>
               <p>Theſe were His Qualities, theſe His Crimes, for which He deſerved Death from thoſe, who had no other reaſon to implead their Soveraign, than a certain <hi>Roman</hi> had to ſue his fellow Citizen at Law, becauſe he would not take that Dagger deep enough into his own bowels wherewith he ſtrove to ſtab him.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:96812:18"/>
               <p>And now, <hi>Behold the man.</hi> Such a Perſon this day dying not like <hi>one of the Princes,</hi> but the vileſt of Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors, murdered with all the Formalities of Juſtice and Devotion, by ſuch as had no power at all over the life of the meaneſt of their fellow ſubjects; A vertuous, Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Prince, Profeſſing the ſame Proteſtant Religion and expreſſing the power of it, in his life and at his death, beyond the moſt conſcientious of private men. The Common Shepherd <hi>led like a Sheep to the ſlaughter,</hi> after ſo many Declarations publiſhed and Profeſſions made for his Safety and Honour, in cold blood, moſt bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barouſly Butchered on a Scaffold, by the hand of the Hangman, before that part of His Palace where He had ſo often appeared in State: What name ſhall we find for ſuch a wickedneſs? A crime black as that Hell it came from, and which nothing can equal but the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of it. A crime ſo infamous to the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo ſcandalous to the Proteſtant Religion, of ſuch dangerous conſequence to all Soveraign Princes, and of ſuch pernitious laſting effects to the Church and State we live in, that 'tis to be fear'd its Malignity may reach Poſterity, and 'twere happy for us if the Example might dye with it's Authors. Theſe indeed, ſome of them, have received the juſt recompence of their reward, and their Puniſhment has been ſignal as their Villany. God has at laſt burnt thoſe rods wherewith he ſcourged this his ſervant, and <hi>their Calamity</hi> did <hi>ariſe</hi> ſo <hi>ſuddainly,</hi> that Themſelves ſcarce foreſaw it. Theſe Malignant Comets, having blazed a little while, quickly expired in a ſtench. Their Riſe was ſuddain, and their Fall too. Children remember the beginning of their glory, and old men have liv'd to ſee an end of it. They are now the Hatred of all men, and ſhall no doubt hereafter be the hiſſing of all Nations. Theſe <hi>Sons of Zeruiah</hi> too <hi>ſtrong</hi> for their Prince, have not been found ſo for the Almighty. For what has been the effect of all their
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:96812:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> Policy but deſtruction to theſe <hi>Achitophels</hi> and glory to our <hi>David?</hi> That <hi>ſtone</hi> which theſe <hi>Babel Builders re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, is now become the head of the Corner.</hi> God has ſet his Poſterity <hi>Upon his Holy hill of Sion,</hi> and may it like that <hi>Sion never be removed, but ſtand faſt for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</hi> May <hi>the Scepter never depart from</hi> this <hi>Jacob,</hi> nor Seed from his Loins, until <hi>Shilo</hi> come again.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <p>To conclude; Let us pay Him, who this day ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changed a Temporal for an Eternal Crown, that Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and Reſpect which is due to the memory of ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious a Martyr. And the beſt way to do it will be to honour Him in Him, who is his ſecond Self, the undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Heir of his Crown and Vertues, his <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the lively <hi>Image</hi> and <hi>Superſcription</hi> of this Great <hi>Caeſar.</hi> And while we <hi>Render</hi> unto that <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Son the honour due to Him, we ſhall at the ſame time <hi>Render unto God the things that be Gods,</hi> that honour and obedience we owe Him, who has twiſted the King's honour with his own, for, <hi>Fear God and honour the King,</hi> are inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and They who ſo <hi>honour</hi> God in his Vicegerent, Himſelf will alſo <hi>honour,</hi> and make them Kings too here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, <hi>Which God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATUM.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 4. <hi>line</hi> 34. for <hi>thoſe</hi> read <hi>theſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:96812:19"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
